School of Engineering, RMIT University
Melbourne, VIC 3000, Australia

2 +61 (3) 9925 1473

2 beth.jelfs@rmit.edu.au

4 beteje.github.io

bethjelfs

C beteje

# Beth Jelfs

My research focusses on adaptive signal processing especially statistical signal processing and signal characterisation. At the core of all my research is the belief that understanding more about the nature of signal generation mechanisms can aid and inform our choice of machine learning algorithms. I have worked on the theoretical foundations of this approach and have applied my work to a wide range of problems particularly with reference to biomedical and neural applications.

## Education

# PhD Electrical & Electronic Engineering

April 2010

Imperial College London, UK

Thesis: Collaborative Adaptive Filtering for Machine Learning Awarded Engineering & Physical Sciences Research Council

Doctoral Training Award

# MEng Electronic & Software Engineering

July 2005

University of Leicester, UK

1st Class Honours

Awarded British Computer Society's prize for best graduating student

# Research Experience

# **Lecturer (Assistant Professor)**March 2021 – Present

# Vice-Chancellor's Research Fellow

March 2017 – March 2021

School of Engineering, RMIT University, Australia My research is on adaptive signal processing algorithms for signal characterisation and machine learning, projects include:

- Development of time-varying delay estimation algorithms;
- Integration of image processing & machine learning for tracking cellular & tissue responses
- Simulation platform for prediction of station-keeping for highaltitude balloons.

# Research Fellow

June 2015 – October 2016

Postdoctoral Fellow

August 2013 - May 2015

Dept. Electronic Engineering, City University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong Coordinated project "Fingers Working in Coordination: Hierarchy of EEG, EMG and Kinematics" funded by the Hong Kong Research Grant Council.

Simultaneously developed a project as part of the Centre for Biosystems, Neuroscience, and Nanotechnology on computational methods for neural synchronization & information transfer.

### Postdoctoral Research Associate

Dept. Medical Physics & Bioengineering, University College London, UK June 2011 – June 2013 Responsible for designing the signal processing aspects of project "Integrating monitoring & modelling for real time tracking of cerebral circulation & metabolism" funded by Wellcome Trust Project Grant.

## Postdoctoral Research Assistant

Dept. Chemistry & Dept. Physics, University of Oxford, UK June 2010 – June 2011 Developed statistical signal processing techniques to study nanopore technology and the accuracy of classification for DNA sequencing.

## Select Publications

Self-Recalibrating Surface EMG
Pattern Recognition for
Neuroprosthesis Control Based on
Convolutional Neural Network

X. Zhai, **B. Jelfs**, R.H.M. Chan and C. Tin Frontiers in Neuroscience 2017, vol. 11, no. 379.

Impairment of Cognitive Function by Chemotherapy: Association with the Disruption of Phase-Locking and Synchronization in Anterior Cingulate Cortex

L. Mu, J. Wang, B. Cao, **B. Jelfs**, R.H.M. Chan, X. Xu *et al. Molecular Brain*2015, vol. 8, no. 32 pp. 200–210.

Modelling Noninvasively Measured Cerebral Signals During a Hypoxemia Challenge: Steps Towards Individualised Modelling

> B. Jelfs, M. Banaji, I. Tachtsidis, C.E. Cooper and C.E. Elwell PLoS One 2012, vol. 7, no. 6:e38297.

An Adaptive Approach for the Identification of Improper Complex Signals

B. Jelfs, D. Mandic and S. Douglas Signal Processing 2012, vol. 92, no. 2, pp. 335–344.

An Augmented Echo State Network for Nonlinear Adaptive Filtering of Complex Valued Real World Signals

Y. Xia, **B. Jelfs**, M. Van Hulle, J. Principe and D. Mandic *IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks* 2011, vol. 22, no. 1, pp. 74–83. While electromyography provides a valuable tool for classification of hand movements, slow training or the need to retrain are major limitations in the uptake and continued use of powered upper limb prosthetics. This paper proposed a method for recalibrating a classifier which reduces the need for lengthy training. By using the spectrogram of short segments of data we are able to provide reliable features and recalibrating using data from the previous session improves the classification performance while keeping the time delays below what is considered acceptable by users.

This paper was produced as part of a collaboration with neuroscientists to investigate novel methods to analyse the relationship between neural spiking and local field potentials (LFP) in electrophysiology data and highlights how computational techniques can aid our understanding of neurology. The study was the first to investigate the synaptic plasticity associated with a model of chemotherapy known to produce emotional and cognitive deficits, showing the phase locking of neural spiking was disrupted and the LFP between regions of the brain were desynchronized.

This paper shows how mathematical modelling can be used to interpret physiological data. Key to this is how differences between data and model can raise questions regarding physiology and the reliability and meaning of signals. We show that optimisation, informed by discussion with clinical collaborators, can be used to increase the predictive power of the model. This also allows us to identify discrepancies between the model and the data and determine the parameters of most clinical significance.

Complex data occurs in a wide range of real-world situations and understanding the nature of this data allows us to select appropriate modelling/machine learning techniques. Despite this many methods are block-based or suitable only for off-line processing. To overcome this limitation an adaptive method for identification of improper complex signals in real-time is presented. As part of this study an overview of second order noncircularity (improperness) and widely linear autoregressive modelling is provided which highlights the need for the use of the full second order statistics.

This paper presents an echo state network (ESN) for nonlinear adaptive filtering of the generality of complex-valued signals produced as part of the EU FP6 Neuroprobes project. The echo state architecture reduces the complexity of standard recurrent neural networks, augmented complex statistics allow the ESN to deal with a wide range of complex data and the introduction of a nonlinear output layer prevents slow convergence. This results in a framework with the ability to deal with data with large dynamics and process bivariate signals with strong component correlations.

### Grants & Awards

#### **Ideation Challenge**

SmartSat Cooperative Research Centre

2020

Goal: Development of a vision based attitude estimation system for high altitude platforms.

Role: Successfully lead a project to rapidly conceive and produce a minimum viable product. This has been invited to be developed into a more complete system in a subsequent project.

## **Project for the Defence Artificial** Intelligence Centre

Trusted Autonomous Systems Defence Cooperative Research Centre

2020-2021

Goal: Performance assessment for a self-organising low-cost, high altitude balloon constellation for persistent surveillance and communications.

Role: Development of a simulation platform to allow assessment of performance based on real and simulated data.

#### Maxwell Eagle Endowment Award

RMIT University

Goal: Using machine-based learning to develop prognostics of CAR T cell outcomes in older patients.

Role: Developing image processing and predictive machine learning algorithms.

#### **Capability Development Fund**

RMIT University

2019

2020

Goal: High throughput platform for tracking cellular response. Role: Creating efficient image processing algorithms for development of high volume machine learning architecture.

# **Global Connections Fund Bridging**

muscle fatigue in collaboration with PLUX Wireless Biosignals Australian Academy of Technology

a Portuguese SME. Role: Successfully designed new algorithms to assess muscle status in real time.

Goal: Developing the framework for problem based learning

Goal: Development of a wireless portable device to monitor

# Sciences and Engineering 2017-2018

Scheme for Teaching and Learning Research RMIT University

workshop style education. Role: Design of framework.

2017

Vice-Chancellor's Research Fellowship

RMIT University 2017-2021

Goal: To investigate the use of time-varying algorithms in the assessment of biomedical data for machine learning applications. Role: Sole investigator, project design, management and dissemination of results.

# Research Exchange Project

BayChina 2015

Collaboration with Neuroscientific Theory Group at TU München.

#### **Best Student Paper Award**

International Symposium on Neural Networks

2010

For paper "Modelling of Brain Consciousness based on Collaborative Adaptive Filters".

#### **Academic Research Collaboration Project**

British Council and DAAD

Collaboration with TU München and the Max-Planck-Institute for Dynamics and Self-Organization.

# 2008 **International Travel Grant**

Royal Academy of Engineering

Awarded to attend IEEE International Conference on Acoustics Speech and Signal Processing.

2007

# Teaching Experience

### Lecturer, Computer and Network Security

RMIT University 2021

Delivery & redesign of teaching materials for the computer security aspects of a technical elective for 4th year undergraduate and taught masters with  $\sim 50$  students.

# **Tutor, Engineering Computing**

**RMIT** University 2021

Delivering C++ tutorials as part of a core 2nd year undergraduate engineering course with  $\sim 200$  students.

## Lecturer, Signals & Systems 1

RMIT University 2019-2020

Offshore course taught at School for Higher and Professional Education, Vocational Training Council, Hong Kong.

## **Course Coordinator, Biomedical** Signal Analysis

RMIT University 2018-2021

Design and delivery of a core 3rd year undergraduate course in biomedical engineering and technical elective for electronic engineering with  $\sim 50$  students.

## Guest Lecturer, Brain Machine Interface: Technology, Culture, and Society

City University of Hong Kong 2014-2015

Lecturing on BMI Technology & Neural Computation for a university elective with  $\sim 200$  students.

## **International Transition Team Graduate Teaching Assistant**

City University of Hong Kong 2013-2015

Providing English language support including student tutorials, proofreading of academic papers & preparation of teaching materials.

### **Tutor, Communications I**

Imperial College London 2006-2008

Teaching study groups of  $\sim 30$  students for a core 1st year undergraduate course in electronic engineering.

# Service to Field

# **Associate Editor**

Encyclopedia BRAIN 2021

Responsible for sourcing and reviewing content on signal & image processing

### **Steering Committee Member**

SmartSat Cooperative Research Centre 2020-Present

Al4Space Research Network: to progress research and development in Al applied to space systems and technologies.

### **Special Session Organiser**

APSIPA Annual Summit & Conference

Multidimensional Biomedical Signal and Image Processing.

# 2020

**Special Session Organiser** 

# Emerging Technologies for Healthcare.

APSIPA Annual Summit & Conference

Vice-Chancellor's Fellows Advisory

2018

Group

# Liasing with Research & Innovation Office to provide improved

RMIT University 2017-Present

Organising events to promote the fellows' research and collaboration between fellows.

procedures for fellows.

#### Organising committee

"enGENEious" conference, Oxford, UK 2012

Student & Post-doc lead conference on microbial engineering.

# Public Engagement & Invited Talks

## **Engaging for Impact**

RMIT University, Australia 2020

Talk on Tissue Image Processing for Innovation in Healthcare with Precision Medicine session.

#### Biomedical Engineering Dept.

Shantou University, China 2019

Invited lecture series on biomedical signal processing.

### Bioinformatics Network Symposium

RMIT University, Australia 2019

Talk on Machine Learning for High Throughput Cell Imaging.

#### Pint of Science

London, UK 2013

Event manager for science festival for the general public.

#### **UCL** Outreach

University College London, UK

2011-2013

Lead demonstrations and talks with school children for events including:

- Medical Physics Masterclass;
- Women in Engineering Taster Day;
- University Challenge Event.

#### **Doctoral Training Centre**

University of Oxford, UK 2011

Talk on DNA Nanopore Sequencing.

#### **Faculty of Computer Science**

University of Applied Sciences Schmalkalden, Germany 2008

Talk on Signal Modality Characterisation Using Collaborative Adaptive Filters.

# Professional Associations

## Asia-Pacific Signal & Information Processing Association (APSIPA) 2018-present

- Member Biomedical Signal Processing & Systems Technical Committee

## Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers

2006-present

#### Member

Member

- Affiliate member of Bio Imaging and Signal Processing Technical Committee
- Member of Signal Processing Society
- Member of Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society